Guide to the John H. Bushnell Papers, 1950-1976
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
John H. Bushnell Papers
1950-1976
Bushnell, John H.
1.2 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Field notes and manuscripts related to American anthropologist John Hempstead Bushnell's ethnographic work in Mexico.
Biographical Note
John Hempstead Bushnell, anthropologist, was born in Minneapolis May 3, 1922. He did both his undergraduate and Ph.D. work at the University of California, Berkeley. He taught at U.C. Berkeley, Sacramento State College, Vassar College, and New York University. His work at Vassar included a research position with the Mellon Foundation. He also worked for the New York State Commission for Human Rights. His partner in most of his field work was his wife, Donna Bushnell, who he met at U.C. Berkeley. Donna Bushnell earned an M.A. in Psychology from Vassar College in 1957. John Bushnell died in 1999. Donna Bushnell died in 2010.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains material related to American anthropologist John Hempstead Bushnell's ethnographic work in Mexico. Includes field notes, drafts of articles and presentations, and drafts of his Ph. D. dissertation.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Subjects:
Ethnology--Mexico
Places:
San Juan Atzingo (Mexico)
Document Types:
Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Drafts (documents); Maps (documents); Notebooks; Notes (documents); Photographs
VCL Categories:
Anthropology and Anthropologists; Latin America
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, June 2012. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, May 2024.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alan C. Bushnell and the Bushnell Family, June 2012. (M2012-007)
Container List
- Field Notebooks, No. 2-15, 1950-1951; (14 volumes) (Box 2)
- Notebook, 1951 Feb-Mar (Folder 1.1)
- Notebook, 1951 May-Nov (Folder 1.2)
- Notebook, 1967 Dec (Box 2)
- Field Notes, 1970 Summer (Folder 1.3)
- Notes, undated (Folders 1.4-1.9)
- San Juan linguistic notes, undated (Folder 1.10)
- Census, Book 1, undated (Folder 1.11)
- Census, Book 2, undated (Folder 1.12)
- [Census], undated (Folder 1.13)
- Rojas Journal, undated (Folder 1.14)
- Correspondence — Mexico, undated (Folder 1.15)
- "Atzingo After Two Decades: Areas and Agents of Change and Stability,", undated (Folder 1.16)
- Cámara Chapter — "The Matlatzinca of San Juan Atzingo,", undated (Folder 1.17)
- [Character, Cognitive Orientation and Children], undated (Folder 1.18)
- Food Paper, undated (Folder 1.19)
- "Graduate School and Beyond: The Art of Practicing Anthropology,", 1974-1975 (Folder 1.20)
- "La Virgen de Guadalupe as Surrogate Mother in San Juan Atzingo,", 1955 (Folder 1.21)
- "Mothers, Sacred and Profane: New Perspectives on the Virgin of Guadalupe,", 1975-1976 (Folder 1.22)
- "Polygyny in Mesoamerica: The Case of San Juan Atzingo,", undated (Folder 1.23)
- Polygyny, undated (Folder 1.24)
- "Pseudoreality in a Mexican Village: The Generalized Virtue Myth,", undated (Folder 1.25)
- "Psychocultural Dimensions of Health and Disease in a Mexican Village,", undated (Folder 1.26)
- "Projective Doll Play Reconsidered…,", undated (Folder 1.27)
- Doll Play, undated (Folder 1.28)
- "Some Observations on the Nature, Treatment and Prevention of Mental illness in a Mexican Village,", undated (Folder 1.29)
- "The Two Faces of the Mexican Peasant: A holistic View,", undated (Folder 1.30)
- Rorschach, undated (Folder 1.31)
- [Rorschach], undated (Folder 1.32)
- "San Juan Atzingo: An Interpretation of Folk Culture in Central Mexico," Ph.D. dissertation, draft, undated (Folder 1.33)
- [Dissertation notes?], undated (Folder 1.34)
- [Psychotherapy], undated (Folder 1.35)
- [Witchcraft], undated (Folder 1.36)
- Reprints, undated (Folder 1.37)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Folder 1.38)
- Maps, undated (Folder 1.39)
- Photographs — negatives and prints, undated; (6 envelopes) (Box 2)
- Unidentified audiotape, undated (Box 2)